howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
today's guests are bill perry secretary
of defense in the clinton administration
and he's also had a distinguished career
in business
academia and the civil service mr perry
is a member of the national academy of
engineering and a fellow of the american
academy of arts and sciences and he was
awarded the presidential medal of
freedom
in 1998. his co-author and co-cast today
is tom colina
policy director at the plowshares fund
and the plowshares fund something i
didn't know about but i'm glad i know
about it now
states its mission as help make the
world more safe
and secure by funding organizations and
people who promote the elimination of
nuclear
weapons prevent the emergence of new
nuclear states
and build regional peace together
they've written a new book
the button about the risks of nuclear
war
and nuclear weapons that many of us have
almost forgotten
are still out there welcome bill and tom
thanks jim great to be here yeah it's
great to talk about this topic
you know this amnesia about the bomb is
real
you know i'm going to give a little
example about myself you know i grew up
in a close-in suburb of dc we figured we
were seven
miles as a crow flies from the white
house i was in fourth grade during the
cuban missile crisis and still recall
the duck and covered drills that's
something
those of us who were around at that time
in that place will likely never
forget and i was quite interested in the
topic of nuclear war
i think part of it coming from my hobby
of playing war games the old avalon hill
war games that me and my friends played
from the time i was 10 years old
by the age of 12 i'd read herman khan's
two books thinking about the unthinkable
and even that fat old tome on
thermonuclear war
you know i was one of those nuclear
nerds that could tell you that our icbm
force consisted of a thousand minute men
and 54
titans how about that i could even tell
you that the titans had 20 megaton
city buster warheads and i even visited
a decommissioned titan launch silo and
command center outside of
tucson which by the way i'd strongly
recommend as an interesting tourist
attraction should you be in the area
i even knew we had 41 poseidon subs
later traded in for
what was it 18 or 20 tridents so i was a
nuclear war nerd
but even i more or less had forgotten
that these things were out there
until i read your book isn't that
interesting
it's fascinating and not surprising jim
i think
we kind of came at this uh be for
exactly that reason
that that we perceive as you do that
people have largely forgotten about
nuclear weapons and the nuclear threat
and so really our effort here to try to
remind people
that although the cold war went away uh
30 years ago
and the weapons have declined in number
they're still there
the policies that make them dangerous
are still in place and so we need to
bring some new attention to these issues
to try to make them safer yet jim not
only the nuclear weapons still there
but in my judgment in tom's judgment the
danger
of a nuclear catastrophe today is
actually higher than it was during the
cold war higher than during the time you
had doctor under the desk
and the that adds a real
note of dangerous situation and that
really motivated tom and me
on an education program in which this
book is a part
and actually it makes sense you know as
a former corporate executive i know that
what you pay attention to
your organizations tend to do pretty
well but i suspect
if nuclear weapons are you know not in
anybody's
front and center of attention well
obviously they are the people who run
the programs
it's quite possible that the operations
aren't nearly as first class as they
were during the cold war which
by itself raises risks and we'll talk
later about shall we say
personnel risks associated with the
current epoch
before we get into those risks though
let's maybe inform our audience a little
bit about where we stand
today you know i talked about the
thousand-minute men and the 54 titans
and the
41 poseidons and all that stuff what do
our strategic
nuclear forces look like today well just
to give a brief overview
both the united states and russia are
abiding by
something called the new start treaty
this was negotiated between the united
states and russia during the obama
administration
and it limits both sides to about 1550
strategic deployed nuclear weapons and
by that i mean the ones that are
out in service on a day-to-day
basis so that's 1550
but there are other ones there are other
ones that are not counted
uh by that treaty that are in storage uh
and held in reserve
so we would say there's about on each
side about 4
000 nuclear weapons still today with
another 2 000 or so
uh in in reserve or or in queue for
retirement
and that's a long way from the cold war
where both sides had in excess of 30
000 nuclear weapons so we've come a long
way
but from our perspective uh it only
takes a few hundred to destroy the world
and we have real dangers of accidental
launch
that could result in nuclear use so we
have we have some distance yet to go
yep and then we should also note that
there are a lot more nuclear powers
these days than there were
during the height of the cold war at
least you know we had uk and france back
in those days and china
but now we have israel and india and
pakistan
and a source of mind swears that
switzerland has had nuclear weapons
since 1962
i don't know if that's true or not but
he swears it and unless they're crazy
the japanese and taiwanese likely have
quickly assembled nuclear kits
so we live in a multi-polar nuclear
world where the game theory in a crisis
could get pretty damn complicated
now the other thing that you brought up
in your book which i think you know
i suppose i knew this but again i had
allowed it to slip into the background
is that the president of the united
states
remains the sole command authority for
our nuclear weapons
could you all comment upon that a little
bit this is
one of the most dangerous aspects of our
current situation
the president and the president alone
can order a nuclear strike
he can do it for it any reason or with
no reason
he can consult with others but he does
not need to
he can consider for two hours to
consider for two minutes
in any event if he decides to launch
it's gone
there's no legal way of stopping him
from doing that
this is i think a very dangerous
situation particularly since our forces
are deployed
so that it can quickly be quickly
launched in other words if the president
decides to launch a nuclear weapon
they can be off in the air in a matter
of a few minutes and then if he changes
his mind or if he gets decide the
information that he had was wrong
there's no way of calling them back
they're on the way you cannot call them
back
you cannot destroy them in flight you
will have started a nuclear war
yeah and i think that's really important
for people to realize you know again as
a somewhat of a
at least a hobbyist level student i knew
there was no call back button for the
obvious reason right that would be an
awful valuable target for somebody to
try
to capture but we should realize that if
the balloon ever goes up there's no
calling it back which means that we have
to think through these policies
because the risks are really high you
also point out in your book that the
culture
of the air force and presumably the navy
as well
kind of reinforce this you talk about an
officer herring who during his training
in the air force as a nuclear missile
launch officer
asked his instructors how can i be
certain that any launch order i receive
comes from a sane president rather than
provide an
answer to his questions the air force
simply fired him
that's right jim i mean i think in the
air force there's an assumption
that rules and orders shall be followed
so i know that some people think that if
a president
say president trump were to make an
order of nuclear launch
that seemed unreasonable that there
might be someone in the military chain
of command that would choose not to
follow that
order to me that is not reassuring at
all
uh one because the military culture is
to follow orders
but two you know that shouldn't be the
insurance policy that
that we have for ourselves if we don't
feel that a president
is capable or qualified to make a launch
decision
all by himself uh then we need to change
the policy
and we're certainly using president
trump here
to highlight the dangers of sole
authority
but we don't want to single him out he's
not the only one
there have been other presidents for
example president nixon
who was known to be drinking very
heavily at the end of his term
uh and as well as president reagan
who was known to have dementia at the
end of his term and even president
kennedy who was known to be uh
taking heavy pain medications at certain
times
so certain presidents at certain times
have shown behaviors that we would think
would give us cause for concern
about giving this much authority to one
person
and this is a great example of a policy
that should have changed at the end of
the cold war
that is 30 years ago but we've never
really taken the time to sit down
and say you know we had all these
policies like sole presidential
authority in the cold war
which may or may not have made sense
then but they certainly don't make sense
now uh we're in a very different day the
risks are very different the dangers are
very different
why do we still have these policies well
primarily because we've never taken the
time
to go back and look at them uh and it's
it's high time that we did because the
risks are just too great
yeah and i would also add as people
listen to the show know i often describe
myself
as a madisonian as in james madison the
chief architect of our constitution
and what i loved about him was despite
being a revolutionary
unlike most revolutionaries he was a
very cynical guy
he knew that human nature was weak and
variable
and inevitably we would elect somebody
not suitable for the job in fact in your
book you quote general maxwell
taylor as to those dangers arising from
irrational american president the only
protection is not to elect one
well james madison would say it's
inevitable that we will elect one
so it seems to me amazingly
irresponsible that we still have
a command and control system based on
the hypothesis
that we won't elect one you know again
just from an
american history of constitutional
theory perspective
and jim since you raised the
constitution let me just say that you
know the constitution says that congress
shall declare war
uh not the president and clearly if the
president uses nuclear weapons
first on his own authority without
consulting congress
we would say that is the ultimate
declaration of war
so we see presidential sole authority as
unconstitutional
as well as as extremely dangerous and
for both reasons would like to see it
fixed
and you mentioned in passing something
that i noticed in your book and i
again vaguely recall this but again it's
not front and center this nuclear
amnesia is a real thing that
i hope your book wakes people up from
and that is the united states has not
yet renounced first use of nuclear
weapons
you know obama considered doing so but
he never did
why is that and should we renounce first
use
the answer the second question is yes
the first question
every administration when summoned into
office prepares what's called a nuclear
posture review in which it
thinks through reconsiders and delivers
its
nuclear policy one of those every new
administration is considered
no first use and when i was a secretary
of defense from the clinton
administration
we had a very serious consideration of
it and we were close to deciding it
in our case the tipping factor against
doing it
was that two of our allies two of the
people to whom we
provided what's called extended
deterrence objected
they felt that that would weaken the
guarantee we'd made to them that we will
come to their aid if they're attacked
so for whatever reason it has been
considered by each administration
and each time it has been rejected in
the case of the clinton administration
and obama administration
it was a very close call now there'll be
a new opportunity perhaps in
january for the president then to
reconsider you have to
go through their nuclear policy with you
a very appropriate time
this time to make the right decision and
to decide in favor of
having and no first years i might say
it's not just a matter of declaring
no first use for it to have any meaning
you have to change your policies and
your
and your procedures to make that evident
that you're not going to use the
europeans first now for one thing having
on
forces deployed so they can be launched
in a few minutes
is not consistent with the new first use
yes and also having a single
command authority weakens you know the
belief in the credibility of that claim
as well you know if it had to be
you know the president and two
congressional leaders
that would make the statement more
credible it would seem to me
exactly jim can i do that a word here
absolutely uh no first use i mean it's a
real paradox of history that we still
have the u.s possibility the first use
of nuclear weapons
because it's hard to imagine a president
ever exercising
that authority the only time the united
states used nuclear weapons
first of course was was you know world
war
ii in japan and hiroshima and nagasaki
uh no president has used nuclear weapons
since and there's a good reason for this
is their presidents
really sort of just are repelled by the
notion
of nuclear use and particularly first
use
uh you know any first use of nuclear
weapons particularly against another
nuclear weapons state
would bring destruction upon the united
states
and for the president who would unleash
that you know
create a reputation for them in the
history books that they certainly don't
want to be
remembered for so from our perspective
we can't imagine a rational president
using nuclear weapons first so then the
question is why do presidents
not get rid of this authority well part
of it is that you know presidents don't
like to give up any authority
that they have but in this case i would
say it has a lot to do with the fact
that presidents haven't been willing to
spend the political capital
because it would be a heavy lift to make
that policy announcement
uh and then go out and seek american and
international support
for that a president would have to spend
some time doing it
i would have to spend some political
capital getting it done
it's one of the reasons why president
obama considered it
and then turned away it wasn't because
he didn't believe in no first use
it was because he wanted to spend his
time doing other things and it was going
to be something that was hard to do
so this is part of the reason why we
feel we need american public support
for these policies and that presidents
even if they want to do the right thing
like i believe president obama did they
still need the public to push them to do
it
because there's always some competing
need some competing agenda
that presidents have to deal with that
at the last minute could convince them
not to go that route
it hasn't historically been israel that
has been
the ally that is most concerned about us
relinquishing first use
in my personal experience the the
countries that protested when
we were considering no pursuits were
japan and germany
if israel was doing it they were doing
it president the president that it was
not coming through the system
but both the japanese and the germans
sent representatives
to our meetings where we were
considering the foster view
and and argued against it
just in the obama administration it was
reported that that japan
again was one of the main countries
raising concerns when the obama
administration was considering no first
use
yeah i suppose that makes sort of sense
you could vaguely imagine
japan being under a massive conventional
attack by china
and asking the u.s to use nukes as a
final defense but it's a little
far-fetched but
at least it's not absurd germany it just
seems absurd right
well i mean again you know i think
it doesn't make a lot of sense to us why
allies are concerned about
the united states giving up the right of
first use
because what we have is an extended
deterrent relationship or agreement in
other words the united states says
you know if you don't build nuclear
weapons uh
and you're in a major crisis situation
uh we will come to your defense
that isn't a commitment to use nuclear
weapons first in your defense
it's a commitment to come to your aid
potentially in a conventional
uh weapons way or potentially
uh to use a nuclear threat of
retaliation
if our allies are attacked with nuclear
weapons but nowhere in there is a
promise for the first use of nuclear
weapons
and i frankly can't imagine that our
allies would consider a threat to use
nuclear weapons first
as even credible or that they would want
it because then we would be introducing
nuclear weapons into
their region uh first and and therefore
escalating what could then turn out to
be a broad widespread nuclear war
and that makes good sense even if it
didn't become widespread i mean if
you're germany do you really want
nukes landing on your territory i don't
think so
now you know first use is certainly a
bad thing but let's now get on to the
one that's really
scary and you know as a person who's
played quite a bit with game theory
and simulations of prisoners dilemma and
things of this sort as i focused on
this my hair stood up on the back of my
neck and that
is the danger of launch on warning
could you explain to our audience what
that is and to what degree
does that potential still exist today
it's it still exists today launch on
warning means
that if our command system detects
a launch underway against us
then their concern is that that launch
will be
undoubtedly directed at our icbms in
their silos
and their thought was we want to launch
our icbms before this lands
now considering the flight time of a
missile coming from say russia to the
united states
there's not much time to do that and
from the time
the missiles launched at the time they
detected it can be
five six seven minutes at the time that
they actually get the word through the
command through to the president
the order's due to the president then
that can be another couple of minutes
and so
it comes down the president will have
about five six seven minutes
to decide to launch once he gets this
warning so
launch on warning means if he gets a
warning
then an attack on the united states is
underway then he's going to launch his
missiles in a few minutes
so that they will not be destroyed in
the silos that's
that's that's the thesis it assumes
it assumes that russia is launching
a surprise attack against the united
states specifically for the purpose of
taking out
our icbms and this is the threat that
now the assumption i think is is insane
uh there's no way i can believe that
russia would see any
any advantage of that if they did it uh
it would surely lead to their own
destruction
i met many russians in my time and
including all the
leaders of russia and one thing like two
things i can say with great confidence
is versus the russians are not stupid
and secondly the russians are not
suicidal therefore they're not going to
be doing that so we have a policy
that's based on really an incredible
assumption namely that the russians are
going to
conduct a surprise attack on our icbm
sites
you know the argument that that's
irrational it's you know i agree with it
and the bolt from the blue theory has
never struck me as
likely at least you know as a true bolt
from the blue
however if we go back and look at some
of our cold war history
i'm thinking particularly at archer able
in 1983
you know in what appeared to the
russians at least to be a crisis which
actually wasn't a crisis but these old
feeble guys thought it was a crisis
uh i'm not entirely sure that in 1983
if the ball had bounced a little
differently they might have come to such
a decision that
you know sort of a preemptive strike
rather than losing their capabilities i
mean in a crisis
people can make strange decisions you
know i remind people of july
1914. that was the argument made during
the cold war and perhaps it made some
sense then
even if it made sense then it certainly
does not make sense today
and the second point is that even if you
believe there's some
remote likelihood of russia making a
surprise attack against us
and you say that's something we have to
consider
the provisions we make for dealing with
that
put us in a position where we are highly
vulnerable to launching by mistake
and so you have to weigh which of these
two dangers is more realistic
the danger the russia is going to make a
surprise attack on us
or the danger because of the policies
we've set up our lunch on warning our
quick launch policy that we're going to
have blunder into a nuclear war we're
going to have a launch by accident
yeah that's of course the key point that
you guys make later in the book which
we'll get to
that okay what are the risks of some
real crisis
and again post-cold war probably small
but all the risk of error is still there
right
you know one of the things we did with
the book is is we we put in a preface
where we tried to lay out what we saw as
the doomsday
scenario uh of of things that could
happen with our existing
policies and that is that there could be
a cyber attack right and most people
don't realize that our nuclear weapons
systems command and control systems are
networked are based on computers and are
vulnerable to cyber attack
so imagine for a moment that that there
was a cyber attack by some
adversary who manipulated our
early warning systems to show that there
was a nuclear attack
underway against the united states from
russia
and the president would be given just
five minutes to decide
whether to launch a nuclear response or
not
and that the pressure to launch a
response is increased by the fact that
we have
land-based ballistic missiles icbms
that are in the ground vulnerable to
attack
and so the advisors might say look mr
president
if you don't launch within the next
three minutes
we are going to lose our our land-based
ballistic missiles
and this is the use them or lose them
scenario
that increases the pressure on the
president to make a decision
to launch but of course realize back to
the launch on warning
posture that we were discussing before
if the president decides to launch
that would be before the incoming attack
if it's real
would have landed and so the president
wouldn't know at that point whether the
attack is false
or real and one of the main things we
want to get across
in the book is that if there is an alarm
of a possible attack
the president because of the possibility
of false alarms which we've had before
or
cyber attacks on our commanding control
system
the president really has to assume that
any warning an
attack is false until proven otherwise
and the president cannot rationally
launch a retaliation
until he knows that the attack is real
and so the main thing we want to do here
is to
give the president more decision time
and in fact
take away the options that allow for
quick
decisions and quick launch because that
is how we will blunder into nuclear war
and start nuclear war by mistake
jim i want to remind you and your
listeners that when we first built
our long-range missiles or icbms we put
them in silos
and the reason we put them in silos is
that we wanted to protect them
from a surprise attack and back when we
were building those
missiles in those silos the silos did
protect them in attack
because an attacker had to make a direct
hit on the silo and neither they
in order to take the missiles the silos
are built lots of concrete and still
they're very difficult to destroy and
for many decades
missiles were invulnerable in the silos
but technology moves on what's happened
since then
is that both first united states and
then russia developed
the guidance the technology the
government guided systems that are so
accurate
that they can destroy the silos even
though they have all this concrete stone
so what was it the ninja originally an
invulnerable basing
of the site in the silos now has become
highly vulnerable basically
in effect our icbms are sitting ducks
waiting to be shut down
though i think just to be fair it is
true that as i recall one of the new
start provisions is we got rid of the
mervs which
really made the game theory of use it or
lose it
high stakes so with only single warheads
on the missiles they're unlikely to be
able to take all of our icbms out
well our point here is that it it
doesn't really matter
um we don't need icbms for deterrence
because
we have weapons on invulnerable
submarines based at sea
and so we don't need icbms for
deterrence and all they do
for us frankly is create this false
alarm
stumble into nuclear war danger so one
of the recommendations we make in the
book
is that we should get rid of our icbms
we should retire them
we don't need them at all we don't need
them for deterrence because the subs
are out there and they create the false
alarm danger that we'd be safer without
yep
let's talk a little bit about the
history of the issue in your book
you guys state that both reagan and
carter
remained ambiguous about whether their
policy was
launched on warning hinting that it
probably wasn't
but they believed that the strategic
ambiguity was useful
we then get to bush and obama and they
both
talked about that it was morally wrong
to be at launch on warning and yet once
they got in office
neither of them actually took the
missiles off alert
could you say a little bit about the
history and again the dynamics on
why we're still here where we are 40
years after the end of the cold war i
think a lot of it goes down to this
back to this paradox that i was talking
about which is that presidents
want the flexibility to threaten
to use nuclear weapons first but they
don't actually want to do it
um there's this there's this old phrase
that the united states uses all the time
which are
all options are on the table right if
someone ever says well how about the
united states respond militarily in this
situation
the response is all options are on the
table and that is a veiled nuclear
threat what that's saying is we might
use nuclear weapons without using those
exact words
and if you have a no first use policy
all of a sudden your
threat to use nuclear weapons first uh
is less credible
but the argument i would make is that a
u.s threat to use nuclear weapons first
is already not credible we haven't done
it in 75 years
no rational president would do it he
would either invite nuclear retaliation
against the united states
or make the united states into nuclear
pariah attacking a non-nuclear state
it's just a step that no president would
do
and so it's time for a president to sort
of cash in the benefits
of announcing a no first use policy
which in in our view would be reducing
the chances
of blundering into nuclear war because
we think that the russians uh do believe
that the united states could launch a
surprise attack against them
and therefore they're on the hair
trigger uh in a way that makes it much
more dangerous for us because there
could be a mistaken launch
from russia because of their hair
trigger
status so both sides would be safer if
we moved away
from earth use uh and we certainly don't
see any realistic process that the
united states would ever benefit from a
first use
jim i want to add i want to add to that
that even
if a president sees some benefit to
these policies
he has to consider what am i paying for
what's the loss what the
what's the risk in these policies and
the point of our book is to convince him
that the risk
is that it increases the likelihood of
an accidental war it increases the
likelihood
you're going to blunder into nuclear war
and we think that is the more likely
consideration
and that he has to have that in mind
whatever benefits he thinks he's getting
from not going
no first use whatever benefits he thinks
he's getting from having our missiles on
on a quick launch and allowing the
launch on warning to proceed
there's a cost to that and the cost is
an increased risk
of blundering into a nuclear war and
that to me is the real danger we're
facing in the world today
and that's a perfect time because i was
about to move into your chapter
titled blundering into nuclear war it
was hair raising
you opened it up with a description of
the hawaiian
faults alarm that we recently had could
one of you guys to run that through for
our audience
tom why did you do the hawaiian and then
i'll follow up with my own
experience with false alarms sure uh you
know
having talked to people who actually
lived through this in hawaii
it was quite terrifying um it was an
otherwise beautiful day
in an otherwise beautiful place on
hawaii
and then people started getting these
text messages on their
cell phones uh saying that there was an
incoming
missile strike and this was right at a
time
when people were very concerned uh
that north korea might attack the united
states this was this was at the time of
fire and fury
where president trump uh was exchanging
uh sort of escalatory words
with kim jong-un from north korea
about whose nuclear button was bigger
and it was a scary time
and it was right in the middle of that
that this uh
false alarm came through in hawaii where
people really thought
that they were um about to get attacked
with nuclear weapons
and so they for you know a good part of
an hour scurried around
trying to find their loved ones and
trying to find shelter
until it was finally declared that it
was a false alarm
and so the main point here is that false
alarms
are real uh they do happen
luckily that was not a false alarm
situation that went to the central
command
or to the president of the united states
but it could have
and so the question is if you have a
false alarm that actually goes to the
president
what does the president do and it's our
deep concern that the president would
respond
inappropriately and blunder into nuclear
war
because of the quick launch capabilities
that we give the president and still do
today
jim i think the hawaiian incident served
as a good wake-up call to people
to remind people that there is a danger
in our lunch on warning policies
i didn't need that wake-up call to me
launch on warning has never been a
theoretical problem
when i was years ago decades ago during
the cold war when i was the under
secretary of defense for research and
engineering
i was actually awoken by a phone call at
three o'clock in the morning
from the watch officer to north america
national defense command and the first
thing the general said to me
was his computers were showing 200 icbms
on the way from the soviet union to the
united states
you never forget a phone call like that
now he
quickly happily he quickly went on that
he had concluded it was a false alarm
and he was calling me as the technical
man in the pentagon
see if i could help him figure out what
had gone wrong with his computers
so that was that that was a very
clear indelible impression on my mind
of the danger of lunch on warning
because of the possibility of falsehood
we have had the total of between
ourselves and russia five false alarms
that i am aware of
we're going to have other fossils they
could happen because of human error
they happen because machine era humans
do air and machines do air so it's going
to happen again
and the question is what do we do about
it and the answer in our mind is we get
away from this quick launch that's
launched on warning
possibly which could lead us all into a
a
nuclear disaster absolutely
though of course again to be fair and
honest we would not have launched on
warning in the hawaiian case because it
was
just thought to be the north koreans and
probably two or three missiles and we
know we can absorb that hit and still
knock the out of them if we have to
jim i just want to say the only reason
for bringing up the wine is not because
that was a real danger of a fault of a
launch
just just to remind people the the false
alarms can't happen
indeed and i i understood that i was
just clarifying
the point that the two issues of false
alarm and launch on warning while
related
in that particular case weren't linked
now as you go into this
section of your book you basically
divide the categories of
errors that could lead to blundering
into nuclear war into
three categories one actually what do
you guys talk about the three categories
hell it's your book you can do a better
job than i can i'm sure
well first of all we can have a false
we can have a mistaken launch an
accidental launch
in response to a false alarm we've
already talked about that in some way
you can also have a nuclear war
blundering a nuclear war by a political
miscalculation
the process of a child in my mind
replica for a political miscalculation
is the cuban missile crisis where
neither president kennedy
nor president kakusha wanted to start
awards were doing everything they could
to prevent us nuclear women we almost
plundered into one
because of bad information that the
president has had
lack of information in the first case
but what some of the information he had
was actually bet
for example well after the crisis
president kennedy said that he thought
he thought there's about one chance in
three that the
cuban missile crisis would result in a
nuclear catastrophe one chance and three
where the outcome would be basically the
destruction of a civilization
but when he said that he wasn't even
aware of the fact
that besides the medium-range missiles
that the
russians had deployed in cuba not yet
operational
they also had tactical nuclear weapons
in cuba they were operational and ready
to go with the warheads
and so if kennedy had accepted the
unanimous recommendation of his joint
chiefs of staff
for a military attack on cuba a
conventional military attack on cuba
our troops were met on the beachhead
when decimated on the beachhead
with the nuclear weapons and the general
nuclear war would surely have followed
so this in my mind is an example of how
you can blunder into a war through a
political miscalculation in this case
mainly through bad information and then
beyond that
as we've discussed this very briefly
there's a possibility of the
lapse of rationality on the part of the
president trump's already mentioned
the case historical cases which give us
some concern about that
the most dramatic one being the last few
months of nixon's presidency
very heavily drinking sometimes at the
point of being not fully competent
now at that time the then secretary of
defense jim schlesinger
was so concerned so concerned about the
policy whether nixon might do something
crazy
that he called the general the strategic
air command and told him
do not take any action if you get a
launch order
from the president check with me first
well
it's one thing for him to say that that
reflects how concerned he was but in
fact he had no legal authority for doing
that
and there's no reason to believe that
the general would have followed his
guidance the general would undoubtedly
instead take instructions from the
president
yeah and we have a situation like that
today at least we may well have
and it highlights these risks that we're
talking about so you had a recap for the
audience basically three categories you
could have
incomplete information like in the cuban
case
you could have a unstable or even insane
president
or you could have what we talked about
earlier you know cyber attacks
failed 46 chips etc that are providing
false information
and you know all three of those are ways
that you know if the
signal were dire enough we actually
literally could stumble into a
full-fledged nuclear war
at least so long as we have launch on
warning as our policy
at any time that's exactly what we're
concerned about
jim if i could just add to that you know
it it doesn't have to be that a
president
is not capable all of the time it's just
their president might not be up to the
job
for one five-minute period out of their
entire four years in office
right because you never know when this
alarm will happen when there could be a
false alarm
the president would have five minutes to
figure out what to do
and it's that five minutes that concerns
us
right is the president in a bad mood
during that five minutes
has the president been drinking uh
you know that's in a crucial five
minutes and you want him and
and so that's part of what underlies our
working assumption here that that no
president uh i don't care which one it
is from history
no matter how great they were no
president can be counted on to make that
kind of decision at any moment at any
time
and it's just too much responsibility to
put on one
fallible human being and there's
certainly no reason why
we still do it we simply don't
understand it and just to add to the
historical
uh case you know we tend to think that
presidents have perfect information
um that they always have the up-to-date
information to know what's going on but
of course
you know as as bill talked about in the
case of the cuban missile crisis
uh it's simply not true and another
story i would just add here which i
just only discovered in the course of
writing the book was when
president truman was considering using
nuclear weapons
against japan the historical record
certainly strongly implies that he
didn't fully understand
that hiroshima was a city and not just
in his mind might have been a military
base
he didn't understand the amount of
civilians
that were involved and therefore that
actually most of the casualties of
hiroshima would be civilian and not
military so we have a number of examples
where presidents are
grossly misinformed and
is that the kind of situation that we
want to put a president into to make a
decision of that magnitude
on such short notice let that be a
warning to us all right
before we turn to what we should do in
some detail
let's update the current state of play
and things
nuclear you know in your book you call
out the fact that
one big decision that was made in the
early part of the century
was us withdrawing from the abm treaty
you know we say it's for defense against
north korea or iran
and the russians assume the worst what's
been the result of that with respect to
the nuclear posture of the u.s and
russia
well jim great point um you know the abm
treaty just so the listeners understand
was negotiated by the nixon
administration
way back in 1972 with russia
and it basically said that neither
country
would deploy a nationwide defense
against nuclear attack now that sounds
to most people to be counterintuitive
right why would you
uh prohibit yourself from deploying a
defense
well the reason is is that at the time
and i would argue
still today we don't have the technology
to make a missile defense effective
now you can still deploy one and in fact
the united states has
uh deployed missile defenses but that
doesn't mean they're going to work
and what happens is certainly in the
russian case
the way that the russians respond is
that they will leave themselves enough
margin to have enough offensive missiles
to overwhelm any defenses we deploy
and so what this has done is created a
floor
below which the russians simply are much
more resistant to reduce their nuclear
forces
so we are in a situation now where
russia is resisting
reducing nuclear weapons that pose a
real
uh and present danger to the united
states
because we've deployed missile defenses
that in our view
don't work and wouldn't be effective
against that threat
and the reason we did this is politics
right it's very hard to or
argue with the american people we shall
remain defenseless
we shall not build missile defenses but
the reality is that that's what we
should do
because the technology doesn't work and
by deploying them
we've only increased the nuclear forces
uh aimed against us or
i should say prevented russia from going
as far
as they might otherwise go with nuclear
reductions
jim i want to elaborate on one point
here policy missile defense systems
do work in the sense that if a missile
is fired
at the united states we can
have a missile defense intercept to go
after and have a good chance
of hitting it but that's assuming
a single warhead but our system or any
such system can be saturated you'd have
more than
one maybe five or ten or a hundred and
we have no possibility of defending
against a mass attack like that and to
further elaborate that
even in a country like north korea which
does not have that many
missiles to attack us with they can put
t coils up as well
and the system we have is vulnerable
to decoys so launching if north korea
say could launch
five or ten missiles at it it would look
it could look to the fence system like
500 or a thousand
and so any defense system can be
saturated
and this system is particularly
susceptible to saturation because it's
so easy and simple
to build realistic looking decoys
for an intercept that's going to occur
in outer space which is where our system
works
sorry about getting into a little bit of
technical detail on that but it's
important to understand that it's not
just that our system
wasn't designed right it's just every
system in that sort is capable of being
saturated
being defeated by being saturated and
it's very easy to saturate with putting
decoys
along with your missiles yep and i love
you make that point i mean
i as a you know civilian nuclear
hobbyist in the 1980s did a little bit
of math and realized
that mid-course abm could never work for
exactly that reason
you know in space where there's no air
drag to separate a heavy warhead from a
you know a light mylar balloon they both
move at the same speed
the opportunity to out decoy is always
going to dominate the ability
to knock down missiles in the mid-course
i mean at launch you have a chance to
take them out and terminally you have a
chance to take them out
but i'm frankly amazed that a bunch of
smart folks
who made the decision to proceed with
mid-course interception
didn't do the simple math and realized
that it was an impossible
project that's the fundamental point
and i would elaborate on that point by
saying that the tactical missile defense
systems we have
which defend our troops in the theater
operate
at the terminal end of the in support
where that's no longer no longer true so
we do have
effective missile defense systems in the
tactical field
but as long as our strategic systems the
ones that defend against the icbm attack
as long as they're designed to operate
in outer space they will be highly
susceptible to decoys
for the reason you describe yep and
while terminal defense is
at least theoretically possible we had
the what was it the sprint system at one
point that was
a terminal defense system i don't know
whatever became of that my calculations
in 1985
said that's at least possible unlike the
mid course which is just a fool's errand
and yet nonetheless how many billions of
dollars did we spend on it a shitload
as far as i can recall let's see moving
on to other current events before we
turn
to what to do about it the russians seem
to be
rather blatantly violating the
intermediate-range nuclear
forces treaty the inf treaty so-called
and they've also oddly i don't know what
this is about have been
violating the open skies treaty and has
basically pushed the u.s to withdraw
from open skies
what are the russians up to why are they
doing this and what does it mean for our
strategic posture
the russians have been bad actors in
many respects i think even more
importantly
is the bad actions in ukraine but on the
other hand the russians also have
4 000 nuclear weapons of which 1550 are
deployed
and presumably muslim deployed against
us
so we have they're the only country in
the world as
one of their commentators once said on
russian television
that can turn the united states into
radioactive ash
so that's a reality we have to deal with
the russians
the reason it's so hard to do them is
because their actions are so bad in
other fields
so the the only solution i can see to
that problem
is we have to be able to separate out
those two variables we have to separate
out
the bad actions in one field from the
strategic nuclear field where we have
common interests
the common interest not to have a
nuclear war not to have nuclear
proliferation
not to have nuclear terrorism so we have
many reasons
that we can deal with them and should be
dealing with them in the nuclear field
if we can only get that decoupled from
the bad behavior in other fields which
we rightly uh poor
of course the inf violations are coupled
to the nuclear posture and that they
threaten our
core allies in europe and as at least as
i understand it these are not
marginal violations you know these are
hundreds of weapons that are
clearly in violation what's that all
about why is he doing this
i don't know why he's doing it but i can
tell you that our response to that which
we're going to build the same weapons is
not a good response either for russia or
for the united states
we need to find a way of getting back to
the russians on this narrow
issue and get it resolved before we make
the world worse off
by the absence of an irf treaty that the
inf treaty was probably the best
nuclear treaty we in russia and those
states with the soviet union originally
ever agreed to and giving that up was a
big mistake
so whatever they're doing in that field
whatever the motivation they're doing
for doing that we need to find a way of
getting back and
discussing and debating this with them
and see if we can find a way again
getting this situation because it's a
bad result both for russia
and the united states and therefore that
gives us a basis i think for negotiating
in a way
yeah i would hope so because you know at
least it seems to me unless we can get
past this inf
issue it doesn't seem to be any hope for
renegotiating the new start treaty which
expires next year i believe and that's
been a cornerstone of our nuclear
you know strategic nuclear arms control
can you talk a little bit about where
new start is
and what do you think is going to happen
well on you start i mean
the good news is that the inf fallout uh
has not
infected the new start situation quite
so much there's been no
evidence of russian cheating or u.s
cheating for that matter on new start so
you know that's all
to the good but the new start treaty
expires
next february and it can be extended
unconditionally for about up to five
years
and so we strongly support uh that the
trump administration
should work with russia to extend new
start
uh for up to five years unconditionally
and that could be done right
now because russia has been very clear
that they support the unconditional
extension of the treaty
unfortunately the trump administration
has been dragging its heels
and has been not willing to support a
a unconditional extension and in fact
has been putting conditions
i would say unrealistic conditions on
the extension uh first you know they
wanted
china to be part of of
any uh follow-on treaty or extension
china has basically said no to that
because they have
so much fewer nuclear weapons than the
united states and russia
uh about one-tenth or fewer nuclear
weapons than
than we do that they made the argument
that you know it's just not realistic
for china to be involved in this point
uh and the trump administration seems to
have accepted that point
but the trump station is still asking
for
changes to the new star treaty in terms
of the weapons it covers
um or the inspection procedures now you
simply can't extend new start and
change it at the same time if you change
the treaty then you have to go back to
the senate
and get a new ratification which we
don't want to have to do
so the simple thing to do here is to
extend new start without any changes
a clean extension as they say for up to
five years and then once you have that
go try to negotiate which we fully
support a follow-on treaty
that could have better verification it
could go after
a wider range of nuclear weapons for
example
shorter-range nuclear weapons that both
the united states and russia have that
are not captured by the current treaty
uh we support that too and eventually to
talk with
china uh although again their numbers
are so so much smaller
that it's not clear that they have an
incentive to get involved at this point
but the key thing is that either the
trump administration or
if if vice president biden wins the
election in november
uh the buy administration move very
quickly to extend new start so we
maintain
limitations on long-range nuclear
weapons and then move to negotiate a new
follow-on agreement
if we move forward the way trump
describes
there is a way of dealing with the china
issue which is we could invite
china to sit in as an observer to the
new to the new start follow on
2d talks and then at such time as we get
closer to them in the number of nuclear
weapons
then they can ease in to become regular
part of the negotiation
but being part of the negotiation today
makes no sense
that makes no sense even for the next
few years but we should
be able to have them in the city as
observers so if we reach a stage
where their missiles get large enough
for our missiles get small enough that
makes sense
then they'd be able to move right into
the talks with us okay well i think we
have set the stage of where we are today
and you guys have hinted at some of the
solutions let's get
down to it what should we do as a
country
to address these various risks that are
lurking out there and which frankly most
of us aren't even aware that we're at
risk
about what should we do well uh jim i'll
kick it off and i'm sure
uh bill will we'll follow on you know i
think
our highest recommendation is that we
should increase the amount of time
that a president has to make a launch
decision uh that we're in real danger
of rushing the president into a decision
uh that could be in response to a false
alarm that will lead us to
blunder into a nuclear war that is the
highest
potential danger that we see to the
united states right now
we don't see a great danger of an
intentional nuclear war
because that would be suicidal for both
the united states and russia
but we do see a great danger in in
stumbling
bumbling into nuclear war by mistake so
there's three key
things that we would like to see happen
to increase the amount of time that a
president has
uh one is that we should um prohibit
soul authority
so the president should not be able to
make a decision all by himself
without input from anyone else including
congress or even the secretary of
defense
the president should not be able to make
a decision
on his own authority to launch nuclear
weapons
uh two the president should not be able
to
launch first uh on sole authority right
so there should no be there should be no
first use or prohibition against the
first use
of nuclear weapons that again would slow
down the process
and also help reassure russia
that we're not going to attack them out
of the blue and it would be nice if
russia responded to that reciprocated in
some way
but even if they don't we would be safer
for it
and third you know the way to make a no
first use
policy more credible is
to retire the weapons that we would use
in a first launch situation
and to us the the first weapons that a
president would reach to
uh particularly in a false alarm
scenario would be the land-based
ballistic missiles because they're
vulnerable
uh to first strike they're vulnerable to
being destroyed
quickly so and as we've said before we
don't need those weapons for deterrence
we have submarine weapons that can do
that uh so we would seek
to retire the land-based
ballistic missiles and now is a great
time to have that conversation
because the air force just last week
agreed to a contract with northrop
grumman
which is a down payment on a new uh
generation of land-based ballistic
missiles these missiles will cost
the taxpayer upwards of a hundred
billion dollars
and that is money we would much rather
see spent on higher priority
threats to united states for example
solving
the coronavirus or addressing climate
change
uh or fixing racial injustice these are
the things that our nation should be
worried about
uh and we shouldn't be spending that
money on weapons that we don't need
all right a good concise statement now
how do we do them let's think about the
details
how do we go from soul authority to some
kind of multi-key authority
as i understand it at least the soviets
i don't know if it's still the russian
doctrine but the soviets had some kind
of
three-key system didn't they something
like that bill
yes they did they had it both tactically
and strategically
for example during the cuban missile
crisis
they nuclear the soviets had submarines
uh out patrolling the area
and their submarines had unknown to us
that submarines had
nuclear torpedoes and they had a
three-key system before they could be
launched that's a damn good thing they
did
because that's one of those submarines
came under attack
i thought it was under attack from one
of our destroyers
and he was getting ready to torpedo that
destroyer the skipper was but he could
not get the other two to agree with him
that would surely have caused a general
nuclear war
and so we just missed that one by a hair
so they had this three key system then
for the tactical system maybe still
today
and they also had a three-key system for
their strategic weapons
we understand that today although it's
hard to be certain about this but we
understand that they have abandoned that
for the strategic weapons
and then now president putin has the
sole authority just as president trump
does
in the united states he's nasty but at
least he's not crazy right
at least we don't think so so let's say
we went with a
three key strategic system in the united
states who would be
plausible additional signers that would
be required and you know of course
wonderfully today we have
lots of very advanced multi-key
cryptography where we could literally
make it
impossible for anybody to forge these
signatures
what are the other two signatures that
you think we should add to the president
to launch
i think for to make any sense jim it has
to be from the uh from the congress
that it has to be somebody representing
the car not somebody that works for
reports to the president
but somebody in a different branch of
government and you could do it
various ways you could have the two
leaders at the congress have uh
you want to be bipartisan so that that
takes it up to four
so the minimum would be the house
majority leader
the the leading democrat in the house
leading with the
in the senate leading republicans in the
house lead republican center that'd be
minimally four people and those people
then could
have to sign off long ago we would say
so we would have a five key system
because of our two-party system instead
of a three-key system
okay and that by itself of course would
slow things down quite a bit
of course it would and then that's the
reason you're often given for not doing
it where to me
that's an that's an advantage of it one
thing we want to do
whoever makes the decision we want to
slow it down we do not want a quick
decision
about ending the world as we know it
let's think about
let's think about that a little bit
let's spend a little time into a little
consultation
let's do a little analysis before we
finally decide we're going to take an
action it'll be the end of our
civilization
i want to emphasize that's not being
melodramatic
if we would if we in russia would
exchange only 10 percent
of our deployed nuclear weapons the
result would be hundreds of millions of
deaths
and results would be destruction of our
infrastructure and their infrastructure
and
quite possibly the results because of
all the smoke and sort that
generated by all these things burning
we're going to have an obscuration of
the sun for some period of time
it could be long enough to cause what's
called nuclear winter which is the
destruction of all of our
crops for you for years on end in other
words what could happen here
would be approximately what happened 66
million years ago when an asteroid hit
the earth
killed many of the animals instantly but
the reason
that we had a mass extinction the reason
all the dinosaurs died for example
was because of the smoke and so it took
it up in the air worked their way into
its way into the stratosphere circled
the planet and eventually cut off the
sun long enough
to kill most of the vegetation on earth
yep yeah certainly you know i always
figured the number was around 300. we
want to keep the
total number of nukes on earth well
below 300
so that we don't stumble into those
kinds of scenarios and we're a long way
from there unfortunately right
so a five key system i could see that
being useful
do we need to eliminate the icbms under
that scenario
because there's no first launch
capability there's no insane or drunk
president problem
it would certainly take more than six
minutes for the five people to decide
do we still need to eliminate the icbms
and if so why
because they are an attractive nuisance
and they are so powerful
and so vulnerable that they just invite
an attack they're sitting ducks
and for that reason alone i think we
ought to get rid of them whatever
deterrence capability we think we need
however many nuclear weapons
we think ought to be in the you know in
our inventory an arsenal
ought to be deployed on submarines and
obama's
not on icbms of course there is the
so-called sponge theory which says
oh yeah they're kind of vulnerable but
they'll suck up and basically just blow
up a bunch of empty corners of
wyoming and north dakota any nuclear
weapons targeted the united states so
for that reason alone
having even a very very vulnerable icbm
force
has strategic value well you know jim i
think that the sponge theory as you lay
out
really doesn't make any sense right i
mean why would we want to draw a nuclear
attack
to the united states uh and you know the
upper midwest
has has really good people and i hate to
put a nuclear target
on their backs particularly when you
realize
that you know if there were a nuclear
attack against the midwest that would
not expend
all of the nuclear weapons that russia
has russia could attack the midwest
as well as the coasts uh they don't have
to make a choice
in that regard uh and so the sponge
theory
you know i think it doesn't hold up to a
simple analysis
which said we didn't have the icbms at
all
would we be worse off and the answer is
no you know if we didn't have the icbms
russia or another country would still be
deterred because we have
invulnerable weapons deployed on
submarines at sea
and they can't attack those weapons if
they're deployed at sea
so they simply would not attack us at
all which is exactly what we want
and so having some sort of nuclear
sponge or nuclear sink
out in the midwest to me doesn't make
any sense
it unnecessarily draws a nuclear attack
to the united states which to me is is
incredibly counterintuitive
and justifies land-based ballistic
missiles which we don't need and as we
see now
are going to cost us 100 billion dollars
to replace
and from a you know game theory
perspective can we do it unless the
russians do it too
if we both did it i could see how it
makes sense but if the russians still
have
all their icbms and now they can
re-target those that were
headed for the missile fields and put
them on our industrial centers and
population centers instead
you know they now have a quite
significant advantage
i think jim the idea of an advantage is
misleading
the russians have enough nuclear weapons
and we have enough nuclear weapons
that we don't have to choose uh in the
scenario i mentioned to you a while back
where
each side uses 10 of the nuclear forces
that's enough to destroy both countries
so we have so many nuclear weapons so
many nuclear weapons
that the idea of advantage doesn't make
any sense with the over cures
is more than submerged in the quantities
of nuclear weapons we have in the
destructive power
that they have okay yeah it's probably
true
let's go down to the next argument
traditionally for keeping the icbms
which is the so-called triad theory
that we can't be sure of the future we
think our subs are undetectable
maybe they are today but suppose
somebody develops an efficient neutrino
detector or something and suddenly the
subs are blazing red on the screen from
an orbiting satellite is it really
prudent to put all of our eggs in
basically one basket
you know jim back in the 1970s when i
was the under secretary of defense
for research and engineering we worried
a lot about that argument and
in those days the thing we were worried
about was no neutrinos but
uh blue-green lasers and satellites
detecting them
there's always been some theory about
how we're going to detect submarines at
sea and basically what it comes down to
it's been a
major counter-measure approach that
technology is developing new ways of
attacking submarines
our technology is developing new ways of
defending submarines but from back and
forth
but over that 40-year period that i'm
describing the submarines have always
had the advantage and i believe they
will continue in the future
we cannot relax and say submarines can
never be attacked
we have to continue to put a major part
of our emphasis
a major part of our defense emphasis on
protecting the invulnerability of our
submarines
and i think it becomes a technological
battle and i think the united states is
a pretty good position to win that
technological
back and forth yeah i mean in addition
to a healthy r d
program the bill describes we also have
an insurance policy uh which is nuclear
armed bombers
so if the subs ever did uh you know if a
problem did develop with the subs
we have the bombers that can be deployed
and so the icbms come an insurance
policy on an insurance
policy uh and a very expensive insurance
policy
at that and one that increases the
danger of accidental war so i think when
you put all that together
it breaks makes a pretty compelling case
that that we don't need them
jim i would add to that that if we're
going to get rid of our icbms
putting all that weight on suddenly not
only do we have to have a robust
robust technological program in it in
the field of anti-submarine warfare
but we probably want to put our bombers
on on air alert
because if they're sitting in the bases
there's vulnerables the icbms are
so the disadvantages of an airborne
alert which is why we don't do it
but we did it for good many years during
the cold war so it can be done
yep that was the old having a couple of
wings of them up in the air at all times
i remember those days
they're not good days i hope we never
have to go back to that but they can be
done
okay i think you guys have answered the
objections and so let's
therefore so order it boom all right
let's hope for the next president is a
sane and reasonable person and reads the
book and decides to do these things
all right this gets us so far but it
doesn't really get us to where we need
to be
the real answer to me seems to be to get
rid of these damn things
or at least to build them down to a
level you know maybe
a hundred worldwide something like that
they're not an existential threat to our
advanced civilization
because no matter how careful we are you
know think july 1914
nobody wanted to go through what they
went through and yet they stumbled into
it anyway
remember january 1861
if anybody had any idea that we were
about to kill the equivalent of six
million
contemporary americans the path of
history would have been very different
so how do we really do what gorbachev
and reagan
talked about doing which is to you know
either get rid of the nukes or get them
down to a level
where they're not an existential threat
to advance civilization
you know one of the persons with that
reagan and gorbachev reykjavik was
george schultz who was secretary of
state at the time
and 20 years on the 20-year anniversary
of the reykjavik he convened a small
group of us to say
isn't it time to revisit the idea of
just getting rid of the damn things
and we agreed and the four of us wrote
an op-ed in the wall street journal
proposing just that
citing the nuclear dangers and proposing
that we abolish nuclear weapons
and for about four or five years we had
a pretty good run in that
including president obama when he was
elected
stating in his first foreign policy
address and made in prague right after
just a few months after he took office
that he was committing the united states
to seek the peace and security of the
world without nuclear weapons
well he failed on that and he failed i
think because
he could not get support for congress he
almost couldn't get new start treaty
ratified by the congress and he just
decided he was going to give up it was
worth the effort
my view on that is that that is the
solution of the problem
we tried very hard schultz and kissinger
and none of myself to try to promote
that
and after a few years finally gave that
up but i think we cannot give up
altogether
and so i backed off thinking we cannot
do that now what can we do now what we
can do now is take
reasonable sensible steps to decrease
the danger
the risk to the social nuclear weapons
to make it less likely
that we'll blunder into a nuclear war
and that's what we're promoting now i'm
not giving up and do not give up the
idea of eventually being able to abolish
new
nuclear weapons but i'm putting my
efforts now on the thing where i have
a chance for political success that can
actually be implemented another these
particular proposals
to take actions to reduce the danger of
our nuclear weapons
tom what do you want to add to that well
i i would i would just add that there is
a
there's a hopeful uh development
happening internationally
which is that there is a new treaty that
was approved a few years ago by the
united nations
which would prohibit nuclear weapons
and make them illegal under
international law
and this is the same approach that the
world has taken to uh chemical weapons
uh which are prohibited internationally
and biological weapons and those are the
other weapons of mass destruction
and if we take the same approach to
nuclear weapons uh prohibit them
internationally
and my guess is that treaty will go into
force probably sometime next year
then that increases the international
pressure on the states that have nuclear
weapons
to get rid of them now this will not be
a quick
process none of the states that have
nuclear weapons
uh have signed on to the nuclear weapons
prohibition treaty but
it's a start and again it's it's how the
other weapons
of mass destruction were ultimately
banned
um and i think it's a it's a promising
direction i don't like
jim i entirely agree with what tom has
just said
but i would point out it's going to be a
long process
i don't have a long five years ten years
a long process
in the meantime we should do everything
we can
to lower the risk of blundering into a
nuclear war
and that's what this book is about well
thank you gentlemen for an incredibly
interesting and stimulating conversation
you know to recap for the listeners the
proposal to correct me if i'm wrong are
basically to do the following
one is to eliminate first use by the
united states presumably by legislation
two is to go to a five-key system
approximately where it would take five
key decision makers
to be able to launch a weapon it would
have to be cryptologically secure so
that indeed all five would actually
have to do so eliminate the icbms
because they're asymmetry about risk
versus power makes them attractors for
drawing
fire up the r d on
subdefense and anti-submarine warfare
and perhaps put our strategic bombers at
least in part back
on air alert is that the proposal
gentlemen
and the proposal on the air alert is
only in the
in the contingent that that needs and
only after the icbms are gone
okay let's make that clear alrighty any
final thoughts or we can
wrap her up thank you very much it's
been a great conversation
thank you jim you did your homework you
had all the right questions and
we did our best to give you the the
right answers and you guys did a great
job and this is
you know particularly meaningful for me
right now my wife and i
have become first-time grandparents just
recently congratulating the last six
weeks and damn it wouldn't it be nice if
that beautiful little girl didn't have
to grow up with the bomb
over her head it would be
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared janes consulting
music by tom muller at
modernspacemusic.com